咱作为发射直播几乎一集没落的太空叉脑残粉
Those of us SpaceX fans that have been following the launches for a while now
可能都已经习惯直播里那些酷炫镜头了
will be well accustomed to seeing incredible camera shots like this
很多超高细节、帅得不要不要的镜头完美的展现了发射流程
These super high detailed shots provide a great spectacle during the launch procedure
两级分离和科幻般的着陆过程
stage separation and the always exciting landing procedure
但这些都是怎么拍的呢？
But how are we able to get these amazing shots?
这个视频我们将了解这类镜头最开始有多么的难拍
In this video we’re going to dive in and look at what makes a shot like this so difficult in the first place
我们要了解一下这些设备现在和之前是怎么用的
We’re also going to talk about the equipment that’s used and how it was used in the past
现在假设你有个相机，要拍一个六十公里外以每小时五千公里速度移动的火箭
Say you’ve got a camera and you’re trying to film a rocket that is 60km away and is moving at 5,000km/h
首先，一个标准的长焦镜头焦距最大可能只有1000毫米
Firstly, a standard telephoto lens will only have a maximum focal length of around 1,000mm
想要拍摄60公里外70米高的火箭，并让火箭占满整个画幅
In order to get a 70m tall rocket which is 60km away to fill up the entire frame you
你需要一个至少十倍焦距的镜头
would need a lens with a focal length of at least 10 times that
另外，为了拍摄平稳的跟拍画面
Secondly, in order to get smooth tracking shots like this
相机需要随着火箭的上升，非常完美地同步抬头
the camera needs to pan upwards in perfect sync with the rocket
这说着容易做着难，因为相机一丁点的运动
That is easier said than done because the smallest of movements done by the camera
就会在拍摄画面上引起巨大变化
translate to huge movements at the other end where the rocket is
如果你用一个普通三脚架，手动对准火箭画面，那画面是这样的
This is what it would look like if you tried to track the rocket manually using a standard tripod
同时如果你没有一万毫米焦距的镜头呢？那画面就是这样的
Now let's say you didn’t have a 10,000mm lens, here’s what that would look like
所以拍这种画面，我们对精准度的需求可不是普通的三脚架加长焦镜头能满足的
For a shot like this, we need something far more accurate and precise than just a long lens and a tripod
太空叉目前有三个主发射场
SpaceX makes use of 3 main launch facilities
东海岸肯尼迪航天中心LC-39A与卡纳维拉尔角LC-40
Launch complex 39A at the Kennedy Space Centre, complex 40 at Cape Canaveral
西海岸加州的范登堡军事基地的LC-4E
and complex 4E at Vandenberg Air force Base in California
这些发射设施都是早在六七十年代就有的
All of these launch facilities go way back to the early space days of the 60’s and 70’s
每个发射台一圈都有几个远距离追踪相机，它们大概长这样
Each launch pad is surrounded by several long range tracking cameras that look a little bit like this
这些运动追踪装置最初是军方用来追踪飞行器或导弹的
These are kineto tracking mounts which were first developed for use in the military to track down aircraft and missiles
回到阿波罗的年代，当时有熟练的操作员控制这些设备
Back in the Apollo days, rigs like this would be controlled by a skilled operator to track
来追踪土星五号直刺苍穹的过程
the Saturn 5 rocket as it screamed into sky
当时，操作员的职责就是保持相机们对准正确方向
Back then, the skill of the operator was responsible for keeping the camera array pointed in the right direction
今天，很多的追踪功能都是自动或者半自动的了
Today, a lot of the tracking functions are automated or semi-automated
这些动态追踪设备可以轻松地由任务指挥中心的操作员远程控制
These Kineto mounts can easily be controlled remotely by an operator at mission control
还能适配各种相机，成为世界上最贵的三脚架
They can also take about any camera you can imagine and become the world's most expensive tripod
火箭公司使用相机跟拍火箭，给我们带来酷炫的直播画面
Rocket companies use these tracking cameras to provide great coverage of their launches
但这些昂贵的相机还会在上升过程中参与分析他们的火箭
but these expensive cameras are also used to analyze their rockets as they go through
而上升段往往是任务最困难的部分
the most difficult parts of their missions
NASA在追踪设备上会同时使用数字、胶片相机
NASA uses a mix of digital and film cameras on these mounts
短距离内的追踪相机会使用高速摄影
The short range tracking cameras make use of high speed frame rates and shutter speeds
这可以让火箭公司以极高的细节分析发射过程中的火箭
which are useful for rocket companies to analyze their rockets in great detail during the launch sequence
他们还会使用比如红外温度相机来测量航天器的温度
They also make use of some Infrared Temperature cameras to measure the heat of the spacecraft
用于航天器再入大气燃烧的时候
as it burns through the atmosphere on re-entry
这些相机在事故调查中也起到了重要作用
Cameras like these have played an important role in disaster investigations
追踪相机成功拍摄到了一块绝热瓦把哥伦比亚航天飞机砸了个洞
Tracking cameras were able to show that a falling piece of debris ripped a hole into
直接导致其在返回时解体，机组人员全部遇难
the Space Shuttle Columbia flight which caused it to disintegrate on re-entry, sadly killing the entire crew
而NASA之后也改进了流程，保证了航天飞机
NASA reviewed the footage and put new procedures in place to ensure that the Shuttle was safe
再入地球大气的安全
to re-enter the earth’s atmosphere
据NASA说，发射场周围还有几个胶片相机
According to NASA, they even have some film cameras placed around their launch sites loaded
每个里面都装有超过一千英尺的胶片
with over 1,000 feet of film each
当然，他们现在还有最新的相机技术，可以向全世界直播4K画面
Of course, they also have the latest of camera technology capable of streaming a 4K video feed live to the world
他们正是靠这些才让我们在发射时看到如此震撼的画面
This is how we are able to view these amazingly clear shots as they are happening
真的很不容易！
We really have come a long way!
所以你们应该知道，拍摄、转播火箭起飞的镜头真的很不容易
So there you have it, the method behind filming and broadcasting a rocket launch is actually very difficult
随着追踪系统技术、相机技术的进步
As the technology of the tracking systems and the cameras continue to improve
我们可以看到越来越多这样的镜头
we can look forward to seeing more amazing shots like this
如果你还有什么问题，可以在评论区、弹幕里讨论
If you have any questions be sure to leave them in the comments below
有兴趣的可以关注UP主，UP主会继续做很多航天的科普视频
and make sure you’re subscribed so you can join the discussion as we learn more about all things space
感谢观看，字幕翻译给虫，记得投币点赞收藏分享关注哦！
Thank you very much for watching and I’ll see you in the next video